Guide to the Oscar Michel Tschirky papers, ca.1890-1958
Tschirky, Oscar Michel papers, ca.1890-1958
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Oscar Michel Tschirky papers, ca.1890-1958.
3990
Oscar Tschirky, 1866-1950.
7 cubic ft.
Scrapbooks of clippings, telegrams, correspondence, and forms; photographs, an etching, a sketch, a guest book, and a tribute book.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes six scrapbooks of clippings, telegrams, and correspondence on his career at the Waldorf-Astoria, ca. 1897-1950; one scrapbook of forms used at the hotel; two published booklets on staff functions; photographs of Oscar and his wife Sophie Bertisch Tschirky; and an etching and a sketch of the Waldorf-Astoria. Also scrapbooks, a guest book, a scrapbook of congratulatory letters from many famous personalities, and a tribute book given to the Tschirkys on their golden wedding anniversity, 1937.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Oscar Tschirky, Host of the Waldorf-Astoria, New York, was known as Oscar of the Waldorf.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes six scrapbooks of clippings, telegrams, and correspondence on his career at the Waldorf-Astoria, ca. 1897-1950; one scrapbook of forms used at the hotel; two published booklets on staff functions; photographs of Oscar and his wife Sophie Bertisch Tschirky; and an etching and a sketch of the Waldorf-Astoria. Also scrapbooks, a guest book, a scrapbook of congratulatory letters from many famous personalities, and a tribute book given to the Tschirkys on their golden wedding anniversity, 1937.
Also, photograph of the 1890 Supreme Court, signed by each Justice.
FAMOUS PERSONALITIES WHO WROTE CONGRATULATORY LETTERS TO OSCAR TSCHIRKY
Jules S. Bache
Bernard M. Baruch
Nicholas Murray Butler
Howard Chandler Christy
Walter P. Chrysler
Irvin S. Cobb
Grace Coolidge
Richard Crooks
Thomas E. Dewey
Charles Dana Gibson
J. Edgar Hoover
Fannie Hurst
Herbert H. Lehman
J. Harry Letsche
James H. McGraw
Henry Morgenthau
Conde Nast
Ethelbert Nevin
John J. Pershing
Ogden Reid
Edward V. Rickenbacker
Eleanor Roosevelt
Nellie Taylor Ross
Jacob Gould Schurman
Alfred P. Sloan
Edward R. Stettinius
Arthur Hays Sulzberger
William Sulzer
Myron C. Taylor
Walter C. Teagle
Thomas J. Watson
Felix M. Warburg
Owen D. Young
SUBJECTS
Names:
Tschirky, Oscar, 1866-1950.; Oscar of the Waldorf.; Tschirky, Sophie Bertisch.; United States. Supreme Court.; Waldorf-Astoria Hotel (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Hotels, taverns, etc. -- New York (N.Y.); Presidents. -- United States.; Guest books.; Presidents
Places:
New York (State) -- New York; United States
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- 15 photographs of Oscar and Sophie Tschirky and friends (Box 1)
- Mounted tribute to the Tschirkys on their Golden Wedding Anniversary [see also leather bound tribute book] (Box 1)
- Mounted sketch by "Ripley" [Believe It or Not] to Oscar of the Waldorf, 1933 (Box 1)
- Matted etching of the Waldorf-Astoria, by [Andrea Laroy?], 1929 (Box 1)
- Booklet: "Behind the Scenes at the Waldorf-Astoria", ca. 1935 (Box 1)
- Booklet: "The Waldorf-Astoria 50th Anniversary Staff Party" [pages stapled together out of order], 1943 (Box 1)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings, NO COVER, 1897-1904 (Box 3)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings and correspondence, 1904-1929 (Volume 1)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings, 1913-1929 (Volume 2)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings, telegrams, articles on Tschirky, and correspondence, ca. 1924 (Volume 3)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings on Oscar, 50th anniversary of the Waldorf-Astoria, and opening of "Culinarians Home" in New Paltz, NY [later the Culinary Institute of America?], 1924-1950 (Volume 4)
- Oscar Tschirky's scrapbook; clippings, 1937-1941 (Volume 5)
- Scrapbook of forms used in the Waldorf-Astoria, especially in the back of the house (Volume 6)
- Scrapbooks from the Tschirky's 50th Wedding Anniversary, 1937 (Volume 7)
- Leather-bound guest book "Golden Wedding Sophie and Oscar September 18, 1937" (includes photos) (Volume 8)
- Leather bound tribute book, in mahogany case, with signatures of many famous personalities (F.D.R., John J. Pershing, Henry Luce, Fannie Hurst, Grace Moore, Alfred E. Smith, etc. etc.), includes seating plan for anniversary banquet (Box 2)
- Leather bound scrapbook of letters of congratulations to the Tschirkys on their anniversary (Box 2)
- Scrapbook of clippings and telegrams of congratulations of the Tschirkys' anniversary (Box 2)
- Slides - 50th Anniversary, Waldorf Astoria, Mar. 15, 1943 (Box 4)
- Slides - Farm, Aug. party for Dad's 79th Birthday, Sept. 28, 1945 (Box 4)
- Slides - "Oscar of the Waldorf Suite" Raleigh Hotel, Washington, D.C., Apr. 7, 1943 (Box 4)
- Photo: Mrs. Antoinette Fassfind Tschirky, mother of Oscar Tschirky and grandmother of Leopold ('12)
- Correspondence, scrapbooks, photos, awards, clippings & menus (Box 5-7)
- Photograph albums (8) (Box 8)
- Recipes A-Z, 1930s (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  Includes several famous dishes attributed to Oscar Tschirky, including typed versions of Waldorf Salad, Thousand Island dressing, and Eggs Benedict.
- Memos concerning the Waldorf-Astoria, 1936-1938 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
- 30th Anniversary of the Waldorf-Astoria, 1893-1923 (Box 9)
- Day Book - events at the Waldorf-Astoria, 1893-1899 (Box 9)
- Day book owned by Oscar, 1901-1902 (Box 9)
- Book concerning the set up of the ballroom at the Waldorf (Box 9)
- Waldorf-Astoria - book no. 2 - what was served (Box 9)
- Herbert Hoover (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Dwight D. Eisenhower (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Menu - St. Andrew's Society Anniversary Dinner, 1854 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- William H. Taft, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Harry Truman (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Calvin Coolidge (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Signed poster for John J. Pershing honorary dinner, September 10, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Signed letter from Ministere des Affaires Etrangeres (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Envelope with writing and profile of Tschirky, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Photograph and articles on Oscar's Swiss chalet model (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Newspaper articles, 1925-1958 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Birthday celebration pamphlets, 1935-1937 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Signed pamphlet and photograph by Eric Hauser, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Menu notes and recipes, correct set up for table notes, 1915-1917 (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Pamphlets and advertisements, 1932-1942 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Clippings from Redbook and Life, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Photograph of Ye Pur Lee, Ching Dynasty ambassador, 1897 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Personal letters, 1930-1950 (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Autographed photographs (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Award and medal from the French Minister of Agriculture (Folder 1)
- Photograph of the 1890 Supreme Court, signed by each Justice, 1890 (Folder 1)
- Portrait of Francis J. Spellman, Undated (Folder 1)
- Signed photo of a couple, signatures illegible except for "George", 1941 (Folder 1)
- Photo of Waldorf-Astoria during parade, Undated (Folder 1)
- Photo - first annual "Oscar" dinner, Geneva Executive Club, Waldorf-Astoria, 1953-10-12 (Folder 1)
- Drawing of Madison Cottage print, Undated (Folder 1)
- Photo - dinner offered by the Incorporated Association of Hotels and Restaurants to Mr. and Mrs. Oscar Tschirky, the Savoy Hotel, London, 1924-09-30 (Folder 2)
- New York Times article on Tschirky, 1937-10-03 (Folder 2)
- American National Red Cross certificate, 1916-07-01 (Folder 2)
- Societe Culinaire Philanthropique - certificate to Mr. and Mrs. Oscar Tschirky on their wedding anniversary - signed by president, vice president and secretary, Undated (Folder 2)
- Menu for "Narsai's" restaurant, Undated (Folder 2)
- Honorary membership certificate - International Geneva Association, 1920-03-11 (Folder 2)
- Movie films
  - 7" reels
    - Farm, New Paltz, N.Y., 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    - Farm, New Paltz, N.Y., barns, cows and hurricane, Kingston, N.Y., 1938 (Box 4)
    - Testimonial Banquet at Waldorf; 50th wedding anniversary of Oscar & Sophie, September-October 1937 (Box 4)
    - Farm, New Chalet, and 82nd Birthday of Oscar, 1938, 1941, 1947 (Box 4)
    - Farm, Christmas Eve, New Year, Dad & Major, 1938-1939 (Box 4)
    - Farm, New Paltz, N.Y., Interiors, 1938 (Box 4)
    - Farm, New Paltz, N.Y., Rathskeller, Dad's Chalet Model; birthday of Mrs. Oscar (Sophie); 51st wedding anniversary of Oscar & Sophie, c. June-September 1938 (Box 4)
  - 3 1/2" reel
    - "Dad on Farm", July 4, 1948 (Box 4)